<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="transformations/cubedoc2xhtml.xslt"?>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" lang="en" xml:lang="en">
  <head>
    <title>
      Command-line arguments
    </title>
  </head>
  <body>
    <h1>
      Command-line arguments
    </h1>
    
    <h2>
      About
    </h2>
    <p>
      When launching AssaultCube, you need to use a small script file, irrespective of operating system. These script files can be modified
      with "switches" to allow different settings to occur on startup. Note: Some of these options can be changed in-game through the menus
      without the need to manually edit the script file.
    </p>
      
    <h2 id="launcher">
      How to edit the AssaultCube launcher
    </h2>
    <h3>
      Microsoft Windows
    </h3>
    <p>
      In the AssaultCube folder, there is a file named "<i>assaultcube.bat</i>". Right click this and open it with "notepad" to edit the clients launcher. 
      <br />Also, after using the server wizard, in this folder will be "<i>server_autoconfigured.bat</i>". 
      Right click this and open it with "notepad" to edit the servers launcher.
    </p>
    <p>
      All switches are placed after the phrase: <span class="code">bin_win32\ac_client.exe</span><br />
      (If you're editing the client, you'll need to add it before the phrase: <span class="code">%1 %2 %3 %4 %5</span>).
    </p>
    <p>
      Remember to save once you're finished!
    </p>
    <h3>
      Linux
    </h3>
    <p>
      In the AssaultCube folder, there is a file named "<i>assaultcube.sh</i>". Open it with your favourite text editor, such as 
      Gedit, Nano, etc. to edit the clients launcher. 
      <br />Also, after using the server wizard, in this folder will be "<i>server_autogenerated.sh</i>". 
      Open it with your favourite text editor to edit the servers launcher.
    </p>
    <p>
      All switches for the client must be put inside the quote marks on this line:
      <span class="code">CUBE_OPTIONS="--home=${HOME}/.assaultcube --init"</span>
    </p>
    <p>
      All switches for the server must be placed after the phrase: <span class="code">./server.sh</span>.
    </p>
    <p>
      Remember to save once you're finished!
    </p>
    
    
    <h2>Client</h2>

    <p>
      <span class="code">-wX</span> sets desired screen width to X, default is <span class="code">-w640</span>
      <br />
      <span class="code">-hY</span> sets desired screen height to Y, default is <span class="code">-h480</span>
      <br />
      <span class="code">-t</span> runs windowed
    </p>
    <p>
      <span class="code">-zN</span> sets the z-buffer precision to N bits. This should be at least 24 or you may experience depth problems.
    </p>
    <p>
      <span class="code">-bN</span> sets the screen to N bits per pixel
    </p>
    <p>
      <span class="code">-zN</span> sets the z-buffer precision to N bits. This should be at least 24 or you may experience depth problems.
    </p>
    <p>
      <span class="code">-sN</span> sets the stencil buffer precision to N bits. This should be 8 to enable shadowing effects, or 0 to turn it off (the default).
    </p>
    <p>
      <span class="code">-aN</span> sets FSAA (Full Scene AntiAliasing) to N samples, i.e. -a4 is 4xFSAA
    </p>
    <p>
      <span class="code">-vN</span> enables vsync if N is greater 0
    </p>
    <p>
      <span class="code">--init</span> executes the init script before starting the graphics and sound 
      subsystems (recommended). By default the script <i>config/init.cfg</i> is used, but you can override this setting by using <i>--init=yourfile.cfg</i>
    </p>
    <p>
      <span class="code">--mod=PATH</span> adds the specified path to the list of directories that are searched when loading resources.
      Use this to add your own mods in a clean way without placing files into the main directory.
    </p>
    <p>
      <span class="code">--home=PATH</span> specifies the home directory for the user profile, AssaultCube will write custom settings
      and files to this directory (recommended).
    </p>

    <h2>Server</h2>

     <p>
      <span class="code">-d</span> This starts AssaultCube as a dedicatated server. 
      The default is a non-dedicated server with only a single client in graphical mode. See the <a href="server.xml">Server Section</a>. 
    </p>

    <p>
      <span class="code">-uN</span> sets the server upstream bandwidth to N bytes per second. only set
      this parameter if you know what you are doing, specifying a wrong value is worse
      than not specifying it at all.
    </p>
    <p>
      <span class="code">-nS</span> sets the server description, for people pinging the server. usually
      does not need to be set if you have a descriptive domain name already, but if you
      set it, keep it short as it may otherwise be truncated, i.e. -nBobsInstagibServer

    </p>
    <p>
      <span class="code">-iIP</span> sets the server ip to IP. this option is only useful for people
      running on machines with multiple network interfaces.
    </p>
    <p>
      <span class="code">-mM</span> sets the master server to use for either server (registering) and
      client (updating) to M. M is the base url of the master server and has to end in
      a / and without a http:// prefix, the default is masterserver.cubers.net/cgi-bin/AssaultCube.pl/.
      If you want your server to be private and not report to the masterserver, use -mlocalhost.
    </p>
    <p>
      <span class="code">-pPASS</span> sets the server password to PASS. Only clients that use the command
      "password PASS" will be able to connect.
    </p>
    <p>
      <span class="code">-cN</span> sets the maximum number of players that can play on this server
      to N (default 6). If more players try to connect they will get a "server full" message.
    </p>

    <p>
      <span class="code">-xM</span> sets the <a href="server.xml#serveradmin">admin</a> password.
    </p>
    <p>
      <span class="code">-rC</span> sets the <a href="server.xml#maprotation">maprotation</a> file, e.g. <span class="code">-rconfig/maprot.cfg</span>
    </p>
    <p>
      <span class="code">-oN</span> sets the server's message of the day.
    </p>
    <p>
      <span class="code">-kN</span> sets the score threshold. If a players score drops below it, he will be kicked automatically. (default: -5)
    </p>
    <p>
      <span class="code">-SW</span> starts the server as windows service and sets the name of the windows service that should be used. Works only for the server binary is started directly from the windows service manager.
    </p>
  </body>
</html>
