<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="transformations/cubedoc2xhtml.xslt"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" lang="en" xml:lang="en">
  <head>
    <title>Get started</title>
  </head>
  <body>
    <h1>
      Get started
    </h1>
    <h2 id="requirements">
      System requirements
    </h2>
    <p>
      If you've played <a href="http://cubeengine.com/cube.php4" target="_blank">Cube</a> and Cube 
      can run fine, then <a href="http://assault.cubers.net" target="_blank">AssaultCube</a> should too.
    </p>
    <p id="minspecs">
      Minimum specs:
      <ul>
        <li>Processor: Pentium III 500 Mhz (or AMD equivalent).</li>
        <li>Graphics: GeForce 1 / ATi Radeon or better.</li>
        <li>Ram: 192 MB ram</li>
        <li>Operating Systems</li>
          <ul>
            <li>
              Windows: 98, ME, 2000, XP or Vista
            </li>
            <li>
              Linux
            </li>
            <li>
              Mac OS X
            </li>
          </ul>
        </ul>
        <p>
          If you can run the neccesary libraries/drivers and are able to compile the source by yourself, you 
          may be able to port AssaultCube onto other platforms. Please note: Other platforms may not be officially supported.
        </p>
      </p>
    <p>
      The above specifications are the bare minimums, so you may need a lot of adjustment to get AssaultCube to run. 
      We recommend that you run AssaultCube on better hardware than this. If you have troubles with AssaultCube, make sure
      that the drivers for your graphics card are up-to-date.
    </p>
    <p>
      Recommended GFX settings for low/medium end machines:
      <ul>
        <li>Resolution: 800x600@16bpp</li>
        <li>Antialiasing: OFF</li>
        <li>Anisotropic Filtering: OFF</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <h2>Pre/post install</h2>
    <h3>Linux</h3>
    <p>
      Make sure you have these libraries installed:
      <ul>
        <li>
          libSDL 1.2
        </li>
        <li>
          libSDL_image
        </li>
        <li>
          libSDL_mixer
        </li>
      </ul>
      Also, make sure the appropriate OpenGL drivers are installed, if they're not already.
    </p>
    <p>
      Note: Files that AssaultCube writes during the game (such as screenshots, configs and 
      maps) get saved in the (hidden) <i>.assaultcube</i> folder in your users home directory.
    </p>
    <h3>Windows 98/ME</h3>
    <p>
      You may find that you need to rename the file <i>DbgHelp_RemoveThisPartIfOnWin98.DLL</i> in your <i>bin_win32</i>
      folder to <i>DbgHelp.DLL</i> for AssaultCube to work.
    </p>
    <h3>Windows Vista</h3>
    <p>
      Make sure you have full permissions to the AssaultCube folder so that your files (such as configs, screenshots and maps) may 
      write there. To do this right-click the AssaultCube folder and then click <i>properties</i>. Click the <i>security</i> tab. 
      Find your user name in the list under <i>Groups or user names</i> and click on it. Press <i>edit</i> and check the <i>Full control</i>
      box. You will need to press OK on the UAC also.
    </p>
    <p>
      More help for installing AssaultCube on different Operating Systems can be found on the wiki 
      <a href="http://assault.cubers.net/wiki/Running_AC_on_different_platforms" target="_blank">here</a>.
    </p>
    <h2>Installing AssaultCube</h2>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td width="100">
          <b>Windows</b>
        </td>
        <td>
          Download the executable from sourceforge. Execute it and follow the instructions.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          <b>Linux</b>
        </td>
        <td>
          Download the tarball from sourceforge. Extract it somewhere where you have permissions
          to read/write.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          <b>Mac OS X</b>
        </td>
        <td>
          Download the diskimage from sourceforge. Drag the contents to your <i>Applications</i> folder.
        </td>
      </tr>
    </table>

    <h2>
      Display settings
    </h2>
    <p>
      When you first start AssaultCube, you will be prompted to change some fundamental settings from their
      defaults to how you would like them. Some display settings can be changed here.
    </p>
    <p>
      To change more display settings, press ESCAPE and then navigate to: Settings &rArr; Video Settings.
    </p>
    <p>
      If you are having technical problems and need to change settings in a way that doesn't start the game
      to do it, you can modify the batch/shell script by adding parameters into it. How to edit the batch/shell and the 
      different parameters can be found in <a href="commandline.xml">command-line arguments</a>. You can also add 
      <a href="reference.xml">commands</a> to <i>config/autoexec.cfg</i> so they automatically execute on startup.
    </p>
    <h2>
      Running AssaultCube
    </h2>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td width="100">
          <b>Windows</b>
        </td>
        <td>
          Use the shortcut provided. Or execute the <i>AssaultCube.bat</i> file in your AssaultCube folder.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          <b>Linux</b>
        </td>
        <td>
          In a console, change your location (cd) to the main AssaultCube directory and then execute <i>AssaultCube.sh</i>.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          <b>Mac OS X</b>
        </td>
        <td>
          Open the applications folder. Click on AssaultCube. Select the options you want to use to run AssaultCube and then press <i>play</i>.
        </td>
      </tr>
    </table>

    <p>Note: Thanks to Harps for explaining the permissions of Windows Vista and KanslozeClown for explaining the process for using AC on Mac OS X.</p>
  </body>
</html>
