<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="transformations/cubedoc2xhtml.xslt"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" lang="en" xml:lang="en">
  <head>
    <title>Get Started</title>
  </head>
  <body>
    <h1>
      Get Started
    </h1>
    <h2 id="requirements">
      System Requirements
    </h2>
    <p>
      If you've played <a href="http://cubeengine.com/cube.php4" target="_blank">Cube</a> and your 
      <a href="http://cubeengine.com/cube.php4" target="_blank">Cube</a> installation runs fine, then 
      <a href="http://assault.cubers.net" target="_blank">AssaultCube</a> will too.
    </p>
    <p id="minspecs">
      Minimum specs:
      <ul>
        <li>Processor: Pentium III 500 Mhz (or AMD equivalent).</li>
        <li>Graphics: GeForce 1 / ATi Radeon or better.</li>
        <li>Ram: 192 MB ram</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      Keep in mind these are the bare minimums, so you may need a lot of adjustment to get AssaultCube to run. 
      We recommend that you run AssaultCube on better hardware than this.
    </p>
    <p>
      Recommended GFX settings for low/medium end machines:
      <ul>
        <li>Resolution: 800x600@16bpp</li>
        <li>Antialiasing: OFF</li>
        <li>Anisotropic Filtering: OFF</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <h3>Linux users</h3>
    <p>
      Make sure you have these libraries installed:
      <ul>
        <li>
          libSDL 1.2
        </li>
        <li>
          libSDL_image
        </li>
        <li>
          libSDL_mixer
        </li>
        <li>
          Appropriate OpenGL drivers (if they're not installed already)
        </li>
      </ul>
      Note: Settings for AssaultCube will be saved in the <i>.assaultcube</i> folder in your home directory.
    </p>
    <h3>Windows 98 users</h3>
    <p>
      You may find that you need to rename the file <i>DbgHelp_RemoveThisPartIfOnWin98.DLL</i> in your <i>bin_win32</i>
      folder to <i>DbgHelp.DLL</i> for AssaultCube to work.
    </p>
    <h3>Windows Vista users</h3>
    <p>
      Windows Vista PLACEHOLDER
    </p>
    <h3>Mac OS X users</h3>
    <p>
      OS X PLACEHOLDER
    </p>     
    <p>
      More help for installing AssaultCube on different Operating Systems can be found on the wiki 
      <a href="http://assault.cubers.net/wiki/Running_AC_on_different_platforms" target="_blank">here</a>.
    </p>
    <h2>
      Display settings
    </h2>
    <p>
      When you first start AssaultCube, you will be prompted to change some fundamental settings from their
      defaults to how you would like them. Some display settings can be changed here.
    </p>
    <p>
      To change more display settings, press ESCAPE and then go: Settings > Video Settings.
    </p>
    <p>
      If you are having technical problems and need to change settings in a way that doesn't start the game
      to do it, you can modify the batch/shell script by adding parameters into it. The different parameters can
      be found in <a href="startup.xml">command-line options</a>.
    </p>
    <h2>
      Running AssaultCube`
    </h2>
    <p>
      <b>Windows</b>: Use the shortcut provided. Or execute the <i>AssaultCube.bat</i> file in your AssaultCube folder.
    </p>
    <p>
      <b>Linux</b>: In a console, change your location (cd) to the main AssaultCube directory and then execute <i>AssaultCube.sh</i>.
    </p>
    <h1>
      Basics
    </h1>
    <h2 style="clear: both">
      Interface
    </h2>
    <p>
      In game, press ESC to access the main menu. From there you can do all sorts of actions,
      like joining multiplayer games and changing settings. As example, in the <i>
        Team/Player
        Setup
      </i> submenu, you can choose your team and skin.
    </p>
    <p>
      The menu covers the most important actions. Further customizations and actions can
      be done using CubeScript: To get a console press T to open up the chat prompt. You
      can use it as console if you put a &ldquo;<span class="code">/</span>&rdquo; (slash)
      at its beginning followed by a command. As example, type this command into the console:
    </p>
    <div class="code">
      crosshairsize 25
    </div>
    <p>
      This will increase the size of your crosshair. Check the 
      <a href="reference.xml#section_Game_Reference">reference</a>
      to see all gameplay relevant commands you can use
      through CubeScript.
    </p>
    <p>
      Hint: Press F11 to get a bigger console history.
    </p>
    <h2>
      Saving Settings
    </h2>
    <p>
      There is the file <i>defaults.cfg</i> in the <i>config</i> directory. If you run
      AssaultCube for the first time it will execute this file. Once you quit AssaultCube,
      the default settings and your changes on them will be stored to <i>config/saved.cfg</i>.
      If you want to reset your settings to the default values just delete it.
    </p>
    <p>
      Edit the <i>config/autoexec.cfg</i> file and insert scripting commands you want
      to execute on every start of the game.
    </p>
    <h2>
      Setting Your Name
    </h2>
    <p>
      Open the console as described above and type the following command:
    </p>
    <div class="code">
      name yourname
    </div>
    <p>
      where <i>yourname</i> is your desired name.
    </p>
    <h2>
      Joining a Game
    </h2>
    <p>
      In game, press ESC and choose <i>Multiplayer &rArr; Refresh Server List</i>. The
      masterserver will be queried and provide you with a list of servers. Do so every
      few days, to add newly created servers to your list.
    </p>
    <p>
      Once you updated your server list, you can use <i>Multiplayer &rArr; Serverbrowser</i>.
      Simply select a server (up-/downarrow) and press return.
    </p>
    <p>
      Alternatively, you can connect to a server directly using this command:
    </p>
    <div class="code">
      connect N P
    </div>
    <p>
      Where N is a valid IP or FQDN and P a password (optional).
    </p>
    <h1>
      Read on
    </h1>
    <p>
      Continue reading in the <a href="game.xml">game section</a> to find out how to
      obtain different weapons, how the controls are set, etc.
    </p>
  </body>
</html>
