<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="transformations/cubedoc2xhtml.xslt"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" lang="en" xml:lang="en">
  <head>
    <title>Performance guide</title>
  </head>
  <body>
    <h1>
      Performance guide
    </h1>
	<p>
	  Getting the best performance possible from your hardware while running AssaultCube, without sacrificing 
	  too much quality is important to most players. A lot of newer hardware will run AssaultCube very well, 
	  with no changes neccesary, but some older hardware may need some optimisation to get a good result.
	  This guide details some ways on how to do this.<br />
	  <b>Note:</b> Although many settings can be changed in-game, for ease of explanation and understanding, this guide only 
	  details the way to change the settings through configuration files <b>outside</b> of the game. 
	  <ul>
	    <li>
	      <a href="#drivers">Graphics drivers</a>
	    </li>
	    <li>
	      <a href="#gengraphics">General graphics</a>
	    </li>
		<li>
		  <a href="#acgraphics">AssaultCube graphics</a>
		</li>
	    <li>
	      <a href="#sounds">Sounds</a>
	    </li>
		<li>
		  <a href="#mouse">Mouse</a>
		</li>
	    <li>
	      <a href="#general">General</a>
	    </li>
	  </ul>
	</p>
	
	<h2 id="drivers">
	  Graphics drivers
	</h2>
	<p>
	  The best way to get the best performance out of any 3D application is using the latest and correct drivers, with the 
	  correct settings. AssaultCube is no exception to this rule. If you have any problems running AssaultCube, always check 
	  your drivers first!
	</p>
	<p>
	  To download and install the latest and correct drivers, follow these steps...
	  <ol>
	    <li>
		  Find out the correct name/make/model of your video card.
		</li>
		<li>
		  Go to the driver/support section of your video card manufacturers website (e.g. 
		  <a href="http://www.nvidia.com/page/drivers.html">nVidia</a>, <a href="http://ati.amd.com/support/driver.html">ATi</a>,
		  <a href="http://downloadcenter.intel.com/">Intel</a>, 
		  <a href="http://www.matrox.com/graphics/en/support/drivers/">Matrox</a>, etc) 
		  and download the latest and correct drivers for your model and operating system.
		</li>
		<li>
		   Install and configure the drivers as per the instructions given to you by the manufacturer.
		</li>
	  </ol>
	</p>
	<p>
	  Some operating systems and graphics cards have other special drivers and methods that you can explore for your drivers.  
	  Microsoft Windows users may benefit from <a href="http://www.omegadrivers.net/omega_drivers.php">Omega Drivers</a>, 
	  some nVidia Microsoft Windows users can try using <a href="http://www.nvidia.com/object/ntune_5.05.54.00.html">nTune</a>. 
	  Linux users might like <a href="http://www.albertomilone.com/nvidia_scripts1.html">EnvyNG</a>.
	</p>
	<p>
	  <b>Warning:</b> If you're using a laptop, you may need to consult your laptop manufacturer for drivers, as laptop graphic
	  drivers are heavily customised.
	</p>
	<p>
	  <b>Note:</b> None of these links or drivers are endorsed, maintained or supported by the AssaultCube team.<br /> 
	  Use these links at your own risk. We highly advise it to be best searching the forums and support pages for 
	  your operating system supplier or graphics card manufacturer if you are having problems with 3D graphics rendering.
	</p>
	
	
    <h2 id="gengraphics">
      General graphics
    </h2>
	<p>
	  <b>Note:</b> Where applicable, if there is a way to change the setting through the AssaultCube client, it has been
	  mentioned (note: in some situations, the drivers need to be enabled in such a way for AssaultCube to be able to change
	  these settings) but because graphics settings differ from card to card, there may be options mentioned which are
	  unavailable on your card or can't be changed through AssaultCube. For these situations, please consult your graphics card 
	  manufacturer to find out how to do this.
	</p>
	<h3>
	  Resolution
	</h3>
	<p>
	  Your resolution in-game determines the amount of detail on the screen. The higher the resolution you use, the more the
	  graphics card has to work.  If you are having problems with low frame rates, lag or stuttering, then lowering the 
	  resolution will yield the biggest result.<br />
	  Note: LCD panels typically work best at their native resolution rather than a bigger/smaller one.
	</p>
	<p>
	  To change the resolution of your screen, 
	</p>
	<h3>
	  Refresh rate
	</h3>
	<h3>
	  V-sync
	</h3>
	<h3>
	  Anti-aliasing
	</h3>
	<p>
	</p>
	<h4>
	  Temporal antialiasing
	</h4>
	<p>
	  Some graphics cards support "temporal antialiasing". It's basically a driver trick that gives the effect of a 
	  antialiasing, but with less work needed by the graphics card. Try it out, as it is a faster method of 
	  antialiasing, but if you don't like it, or it's still too slow, don't use it.
	</p>
	
	<h3>
	  Anisotropic filtering
	</h3>
	
	<ul>
	  <li><b>Useful link:</b> <a href="http://www.tweakguides.com/Graphics_1.html">Tweakguide: Gamer's Graphics and 
	  Display Settings Guide</a> - This link is extremely useful if you know nothing about optimising your hardware.
	  </li>
	</ul>
	
    <h2 id="acgraphics">
	  AssaultCube Graphics
	</h2>
	
    <h2 id="sounds">
      Sounds
    </h2>
	
	<h2 id="mouse">
	  Mouse
	</h2>


    <h2 id="general">
      General
    </h2>
	<p>
	  Physical ways to increase your computers performance for AssaultCube are: Upgrading RAM, CPU power, Graphics cards,
      use a more powerful power supply, use PCI express instead of AGP, etc, etc.<br />
	  If you wish to upgrade your systems hardware, please seek advice elsewhere. There are plenty of resources available online!
	</p>
	<p>
	  When running AssaultCube, it would be wise to turn off any un-needed applications, especially those that suck down CPU 
	  performance and graphics rendering. For example: Turn off compiz, music players, windows defender, etc. Also try turning 
	  down the graphics settings used by your operating system for everyday tasks.
	</p>
  </body>
</html>

