<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="transformations/cubedoc2xhtml.xslt"?>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" lang="en" xml:lang="en">
  <head>
    <title>The basics</title>
  </head>
  <body>
    <h2>
      How settings are saved
    </h2>
    <p>
      There is a file called <i>defaults.cfg</i> in the <i>config</i> directory. When you run
      AssaultCube for the first time it will execute this file. Once you quit AssaultCube,
      the default settings and your changes created upon them during the course of the game
      (and from your autoexec.cfg) will be stored in <i>config/saved.cfg</i>. 
      If you want to reset your settings to default values just delete <i>config/saved.cfg</i>.
      Alternatively, you can delete it using the menus, by pressing ESCAPE and going into: Settings &rArr; Delete and reset all settings &rArr; Yes.
    </p>
    <p>
      If there are commands that you would like executed every time AssaultCube starts, you can insert
      these scripting commands into <i>config/autoexec.cfg</i>.
    </p>
    <p>
      When AssaultCube is started, it will check for the file <i>config/init.cfg</i>. If it does not exist
      then AssaultCube assumes this is the first time you have ran AssaultCube and will prompt you with the 
      "quick setup" menu. This contains settings for you to change that are important for running AssaultCube. 
      Such as screen resolution, mouse sensitivity, nickname, etc. When you press "OK", then AssaultCube will restart to 
      allow those settings to take effect. The <i>config/init.cfg</i> file saves settings that can only be 
      changed before AssaultCube runs, so when AssaultCube first starts, it will execute those settings.
    </p>
    <p>
      Note for linux users: Config files get saved in the hidden directory <i>.assaultcube/config</i> 
      in your users home directory.
    </p>
    <h2>
      Changing settings
    </h2>
    <p>
      Open the console as described above and type the following command:
    </p>
    <div class="code">
      name yourname
    </div>
    <p>
      where <i>yourname</i> is your desired name.
    </p>
    <h2>
      Joining a Game
    </h2> 
<!--Add info about servers being saved in servers.cfg here-->
    <p>
      In game, press ESC and choose <i>Multiplayer &rArr; Refresh Server List</i>. The
      masterserver will be queried and provide you with a list of servers. Do so every
      few days, to add newly created servers to your list.
    </p>
    <p>
      Once you updated your server list, you can use <i>Multiplayer &rArr; Serverbrowser</i>.
      Simply select a server (up-/downarrow) and press return.
    </p>
    <p>
      Alternatively, you can connect to a server directly using this command:
    </p>
    <div class="code">
      connect N P
    </div>
    <p>
      Where N is a valid IP or FQDN and P a password (optional).
    </p>
  </body>
</html>