<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="transformations/cubedoc2xhtml.xslt"?>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" lang="en" xml:lang="en">
  <head><title>Map editing: Beginners</title></head>
  <body>
    <h1>Map editing: Beginners</h1>
    <p>
      Prior to reading this, please learn the controls and interface <a href="mapediting1.xml">here</a>.
    </p>
    <p> 
      To begin map editing, while in AssaultCube, press the letter <b>E</b> which toggles editmode. AssaultCubes map editor is built into the client,
      so its easy to learn and you don't need to download any special tools to get started. 
      <br />Note: Because of how the <a href="cubeengine.xml">cube engine works</a> there are some limitations to what you can create, but 
      there are also some clever work-arounds you can use to get what you want.
    </p>
    <p>
      In editmode (<b>press E</b>) you can fly around in any direction you 
      like and you can even go through walls. <br />This is to make map-editing easier...
    </p>
    <p>
      <b>Tip:</b> When editing a map, make sure you have your settings set back to the defaults, so you can see what your map looks like to the
      average player (example: set gamma back to 100, so you can judge lighting correctly).
    </p>

    <h2 id="startmap">Starting, saving and loading a map</h2>
    <p>
      If you would like to start creating a new map, type: <i>/newmap</i> and then the size you would like (7 is the sensible default) and 
      then press ENTER. If you made your mapsize too small, you can easily make it double in size, simply by typing <i>/mapenlarge</i>.
    </p>
    <p>
      You can save your map at any time by typing: <i>/savemap</i> and then the name you would like it saved as. The map gets
      saved in the <i>packages/maps</i> directory. Save your map often, to avoid the frustration of losing all of your work if something goes wrong.
    </p>
    <p>
      <b>Note:</b> Make sure when you start a map, to use the <i>/newmap</i> command, rather than editing an existing map, otherwise your map may get saved
      a bit strangely. Also note: you cannot put spaces or any illegal characters in the name you save it as.
    </p>
    <p>
      To load your map, type /map and the file name you chose for your map. If you have not placed lighting in your map yet, your map will turn up dark. 
      To temporarily fix this problem, type: <i>/fullbright 1</i>  - this will fill your whole map with light. The fullbright command only works in edit
      mode and is not a permanent fix. To remove fullbright mode, reload the map, or type: <i>/recalc</i>. 
      Note: These commands can be found in the lighting menu (press <b>L</b>).
</p>

    <h2>Manipulating geometry</h2>
     
    <h2 id="co-op">Co-operative map editing</h2>
    <p>
      Co-operative map editing lets you build and modify maps with others easily. This mode allows you to edit maps online with other players
      who could help speed up repetitive or boring tasks, bring in fresh ideas or spot errors you may have missed.
    </p>
    <p>
      To start co-operative map editing, when in a server, type: <i>/mode 1</i> and then type: <i>/map</i> and then your mapnames name and press ENTER.
      You will have to of made a "newmap" previous to entering the server to be able to co-op edit it.
    </p>
    <p>
      You will then need to <b>send</b> the map. You can do this by typing: <i>/sendmap</i> and then your mapnames name and press ENTER. Note: Custom 
      materials can't be sent, they will have to be downloaded another way if you are using them. If you are using a custom "cfg" file, it will automatically
      be sent with the map, if there is a cfg file present.
    </p>
    <p>
      Note: Some useful editing commands can't be used in co-op editing, such as: copy, paste, slope, arch, undo, etc.
    </p>
  </body>
</html>
