<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="transformations/cubedoc2xhtml.xslt"?>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" lang="en" xml:lang="en">
  <head><title>Map editing: Entities</title></head>
  <body>
    <h1>Entities</h1>

    <p>
      <a href="mapediting1.xml#sparkles">Entities</a> are shown as blue sparkly dots when in edit mode. 
      They are used for adding non-geometery/texture items, such as:
      <ul>
        <li>
          <a href="#light">Lights</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="#pickup">Item pickups</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="#spawn">Spawn points</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="#models">Mapmodels</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="#ctf">CTF flags</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="#ladders">Ladders</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="#sounds">Ambient sounds</a>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>

    <p>
      Each of these entities will be explained soon. All entities are added by the <b>/newent</b> command (or through the editing menu). 
      When adding entities, they are always added to the red dot on the corner of the cube that you selected and at the height of 
      which you are currently hovering (note: the physical entity created will always drop down to the ground).
    </p>
    <p>
      Some useful commands to use with entities:
      <ul>
        <li>
          <b><a href="reference.xml#identifier_delent">/delent</a></b> - Typing <i>/delent</i> (you can also press "backspace") will delete the nearest entity. 
          The nearest entity can be found by reading the white text along the bottom of your screen which tells 
          you the type of entity that you are nearest to and the properties of that entity.
        </li>
        <li>
          <b><a href="reference.xml#identifier_entproperty">/entproperty</a></b>
        </li>
        <li>
          <b><a href="reference.xml#identifier_clearents">/clearents</a></b>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <h2 id="light">Lighting</h2>

    <p>
      <b>Tips:</b>
      <ul>
        <li>
          To temporarally light up a map so you can edit it easily, type: <b>/fullbright 1</b>. To remove fullbright, type: <b>/recalc</b>. 
        </li>
        <li>
          Make sure gamma is turned back to the defaults when you're editing so you can properly judge how a lighting will look to an average user.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>

    <p>
      Lights can be added typing "<b>/newent light</b>" and then a number between 1 and 32 to define the size of the light (the radius) 
      and then a number between 1 and 255 to define the brightness.
    </p>

    <p>
      Coloured lighting can be added typing "<b>/newent light</b>" and then a number between 1 and 32 to define the size of the light 
      (the radius) and then a number between 1 and 255 to define the amount of red light and then a number between 1 and 255 to define 
      the amount of green light and then a number between 1 and 255 to define the amount of blue light.
    </p>
    <p>      
      <b>Note:</b> The radius and all 3 colour values must be defined for a coloured light to be created correctly. You can't omit 
      a value as it will not create the light correctly. If you don't want any colour from a specific value, 
      simply use the value "1" as a place holder.
    </p>

    <p>
      There is also a new handy menu that you can use to create lights by pressing L or accessing it through the editing menu. 
    </p>

    <p>
      <b>Tip:</b> If you accidentally light a map too brightly (for example, you didn't reset your gamma levels before editing), 
      instead of deleting lights and starting again, you could utilize the <b><a href="reference.xml#identifier_scalelights">/scalelights</a></b> command.
    </p>

    <h2 id="pickup">Item pickups</h2>

    <p>
      Pickups must be placed strategically through maps and do take some time to position correctly. Powerful pickups should be 
      few and not be too close to each other (unless there is a good risk involved) and pickups should be well spread and not be 
      too high in number. Try to keep powerful pickups away from the spawn area so players are encouraged to leave their bases. 
      Strategy is key! A good idea to keep in mind when mapping is "<i>what would I need here to help me pwn?</i>"
    </p>
    <p>
      To place pickups, use the pickups menu inside the editing menu, otherwise type one of the below...
      <ul>
        <li>
          <b>/newent health</b> - To place a health pack.
        </li>
        <li>
          <b>/newent armour</b> - To place armour.
        </li>
        <li>
          <b>/newent akimbo</b> - To place akimbo.
        </li>
        <li>
          <b>/newent grenades</b> - To place grenades.
        </li>
        <li>
          <b>/newent clips</b> - To place a pistol magazine.
        </li>
        <li>
          <b>/newent ammobox</b> - To place an ammunition box.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>

    <h2 id="spawn">Spawn points</h2>
    <p>
      In AssaultCube, there are three types of spawn points: RVSF spawn points, CLA spawn points and FFA spawn points (free-for-all).
    </p>
    <p>
      As a general rule, you should place as many spawn points as possible in a spawn area so that players aren't spawning from the 
      same point too often. However, don't over-do it. Make sure that spawn points are not too close to each other. 
    </p>
    <p>
      Also make sure that spawns are not too close to any walls and mapmodels so players don't get stuck inside them. Take care when 
      placing spawn points to make sure you face the direction you would like the player to face when they spawn, so that they spawn
      looking in that direction, rather than facing a wall!
    </p>
    <p>
      RVSF and CLA spawn points should be placed in their respective bases. FFA spawns should be placed all over the map in 
      various places (FFA spawns are for non-team type games, such as Deathmatch or One-shot, one-kill).
    </p>
    <p>
      If spawn points are not created, players will just spawn in the middle of the map, all next to each other, 
      so please remember to add spawn points.
    </p>
    <p>
      You can add spawn points through the editing menu, or you can type:
      <ul>
        <li>
          <b>/newent playerstart 1</b> - To add an RVSF spawn point.
        </li>
        <li>
          <b>/newent playerstart 0</b> - To add a CLA spawn point.
        </li>
        <li>
          <b>/newent playerstart 100</b> - To add an FFA spawn point.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <h2 id="models">Mapmodels :: TODO</h2>
    <h2 id="ctf">CTF flags</h2>
    <p>
      If you want to enable CTF mode on your map, place a CTF flag in each respective base using the menus or by typing:
      <ul>
        <li>
          <b>/newent ctf-flag 0</b> - Adds the CLA flag.
        </li>
        <li>
          <b>/newent ctf-flag 1</b> - Adds the RVSF flag.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <h2 id="ladders">Ladders</h2>
    <p>
      Ladders are comprised of <b>TWO</b> peices. One part is the ladder mapmodel which gives the ladder an apperance. 
      The other part is the "entity" which is an invisible force that let's you climb the mapmodel like a ladder.
    </p>
    <h3>To place the mapmodel</h3>
    <p>
      Choose the appropriate place for the model, then, pick the appropriate sized mapmodel from the 
      <i>Editing > Mapmodels > Ladders/stairs</i> menu.
      To place the model with the <b>correct</b> orientation, turn 90 degrees to the left before placing it.<br />
      There is a single ladder rung model that you can use to make different sized ladders if needed 
      (by applying height to the model, see <a href="#models">mapmodels</a>).
    </p>
    <h3>To place the entity</h3>
    <p>
      On the same cube that you placed the mapmodel, type: <b>/newent ladder X</b>. Replace "X" with the amount of cubes
      that the player will need to climb.
    </p>


    <h2 id="sounds">Ambient sounds :: TODO</h2>





  </body>
</html>
