<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="transformations/cubedoc2xhtml.xslt"?>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" lang="en" xml:lang="en">
  <head><title>Map editing</title></head>
  <body>
    <h1>Map editing</h1>
    <h2>Introduction...</h2>
    <p>
      To begin map editing, while in AssaultCube, press the letter <b>E</b> which toggles editmode. AssaultCubes map editor is built into the client,
      so its easy to learn and you don't need to download any special tools to get started. In editmode, you can fly around in any direction you 
      like and you can even go through walls. This is to make map-editing easier.
    </p>
    <p style="text-align:center">
      <img src="pics/editmode.jpg" alt="Editing mode"/>
    </p>
    <p>
      In editmode you may see..
      <ul>
        <li>
          A white grid of squares - This will be drawn where ever you point. <br />Each of the small squares is a single cube. The cubes in 
                                    AssaultCube are known as "geometery".
        </li>
        <li>
          A bigger, blue grid of squares - The blue squares indicate a selection of 8x8 cubes, to make editing easier.
        </li>
        <li>
          Light green cubes in the grid - These cubes indicate heightfields, which will be explained later <a herf="#LINK">here</a>.
        </li>
        <li>
          Some blue sparkly things - These sparkly things are known as "entities", which will be explained later <a herf="#LINK">here</a>.
        </li>
        <li>
          A small white box with a red dot - This will appear in the middle of your screen, you can use it to select geometery, sorta like a crosshair. 
          The red dot indicates which corner of a cube you are manipulating, if you are using heightfields, or where your entity will be placed if you 
          are creating an entity, but you don't need to worry about knowing how to use that red dot just yet.
        </li>
        <li>
          White writing at the bottom - This tells you the locaton of the closest entity and its properties, but you don't need to worry
          about how to use that just yet.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      To get a feel for editmode, press E and float around. Try clicking and dragging the small white box at your crosshair over 
      some cubes (you will see a red box over what you are selecting). This is how you select geometery.
    </p>

    <h2 id="controls">Map editing controls</h2>

    <p>
      Below are the controls that get used in map-editing, you will use most of these controls when creating a map, so it's good to learn them.
    </p>
    <h3>Changing geometery</h3>
    <table>
	      <tr>
        <td width="150">
          <b><u>Control</u></b>
        </td>
        <td width="450">
          <b><u>Function</u></b>
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          [
        </td>
        <td>
          Moves cubes in the floor downwards.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          ]
        </td>
        <td>
          Moves cubes in the floor upwards.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          O
        </td>
        <td>
          Moves cubes in the ceiling downwards.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          P
        </td>
        <td>
          Moves cubes in the ceiling upwards.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          F
        </td>
        <td>
          Makes selected cubes a solid.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          G
        </td>
        <td>
          Makes selected cubes a space/non-heightfield.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          K
        </td>
        <td>
          Makes selected cubes a corner.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          C
        </td>
        <td>
          Copy selected cubes.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          V
        </td>
        <td>
          Pastes copied cubes. <br />Note: It pastes from the upper corner of the red dot.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          U
        </td>
        <td>
          Undoes the last action (only applies to geometery).
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          ,
        </td>
        <td>
          Equalize the floor.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          .
        </td>
        <td>
          Equalize the ceiling.
        </td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>
          H
        </td>
        <td>
          Makes the floor a heightfield.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          I
        </td>
        <td>
          Makes the ceiling a heightfield.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          9
        </td>
        <td>
          Manipulates the corner of a cube where the red dot is positioned upwards. 
          Works only if the cube is a heightfield.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          8
        </td>
        <td>
          Manipulates the corner of a cube where the red dot is positioned downwards. 
          Works only if the cube is a heightfield.
        </td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    
    <h3>Changing textures</h3>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td width="150">
          <b><u>Control</u></b>
        </td>
        <td width="350">
          <u><b>Function</b></u>
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          Home
        </td>
        <td>
          Browses forward through wall textures.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          End
        </td>
        <td>
          Browses backward through wall textures.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          7 (on the keypad)
        </td>
        <td>
          Browses forward through upper-wall textures.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          4 (on the keypad)
        </td>
        <td>
          Browses backward through upper-wall textures.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          Insert
        </td>
        <td>
          Browses forward through floor textures.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          Delete
        </td>
        <td>
          Browses backward through floor textures.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          PageUp
        </td>
        <td>
          Browses forward through ceiling textures.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          PageDown
        </td>
        <td>
          Browses backward through ceiling textures.
        </td>
      </tr>
      </table>

    <h3>Mouse controls</h3>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td width="150">
          <b><u>Control</u></b>
        </td>
        <td width="400">
          <u><b>Function</b></u>
        </td>
      </tr> 
      <tr>
        <td>
          Left-click
        </td>
        <td>
          Allows you to select cubes.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          Right-click
        </td>
        <td>
          Show the editing menu.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          Scrolling
        </td>
        <td>
          Scrolling will move cubes up/down, depending on the direction you look.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          Hold <b>Q</b> and scroll
        </td>
        <td>
          This will manipulate the corner of a cube where the red dot is positioned up/down. 
          Works only if the cube is a heightfield.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          Hold <b>Z</b> and scroll
        </td>
        <td>
          Scrolls forward/backwards through textures on the floor/ceiling, depending on the direction you look.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          Hold <b>X</b> and scroll
        </td>
        <td>
          Scrolls forward/backwards through textures on the wall/upper-wall, depending on the direction you look.
        </td>
      </tr>
    </table>

    <h3>Misc</h3>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td width="150">
          <b><u>Control</u></b>
        </td>
        <td width="350">
          <b><u>Function</u></b>
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          E
        </td>
        <td>
          Toggle edit mode.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          Backspace
        </td>
        <td>
          Delete entity.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          L
        </td>
        <td>
          Shows the lighting menu.
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          F5
        </td>
        <td>
          Toggle ocullsion on/off.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          F6
        </td>
        <td>
          Toggle showmip on/off.
        </td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <h2 id="startmap">Starting, saving and loading a map</h2>
    <p>
      If you would like to start creating a new map, type: <i>/newmap</i> and then the size you would like (7 is the sensible default) and 
      then press ENTER. If you made your mapsize too small, you can easily make it double in size, simply by typing <i>/mapenlarge</i>.
    </p>
    <p>
      You can save your map at any time by typing: <i>/savemap</i> and then the name you would like it saved as. The map gets
      saved in the <i>packages/maps</i> directory. Save your map often, to avoid the frustration of losing all of your work if something goes wrong.
    </p>
    <p>
      <b>Note:</b> Make sure when you start a map, to use the <i>/newmap</i> command, rather than editing an existing map, otherwise your map may get saved
      a bit strangely. Also note: you cannot put spaces or any illegal characters in the name you save it as.
    </p>
    <p>
      To load your map, type /map and the file name you chose for your map. If you have not placed lighting in your map yet, your map will turn up dark. 
      To temporarily fix this problem, type: <i>/fullbright 1</i>  - this will fill your whole map with light. The fullbright command only works in edit
      mode and is not a permanent fix. To remove fullbright mode, reload the map, or type: <i>/recalc</i>. 
      Note: These commands can be found in the lighting menu (press <b>L</b>).
    </p>

    <h2 id="co-op">Co-operative map editing</h2>
    <p>
      Co-operative map editing lets you build and modify maps with others easily. This mode allows you to edit maps online with other players
      who could help speed up repetitive or boring tasks, bring in fresh ideas or spot errors you may have missed.
    </p>
    <p>
      To start co-operative map editing, when in a server, type: <i>/mode 1</i> and then type: <i>/map</i> and then your mapnames name and press ENTER.
      You will have to of made a "newmap" previous to entering the server to be able to co-op edit it.
    </p>
    <p>
      You will then need to <b>send</b> the map. You can do this by typing: <i>/sendmap</i> and then your mapnames name and press ENTER. Note: Custom 
      materials can't be sent, they will have to be downloaded another way if you are using them. If you are using a custom "cfg" file, it will automatically
      be sent with the map, if there is a cfg file present.
    </p>
    <p>
      Note: Some useful editing commands can't be used in co-op editing, such as: copy, paste, slope, arch, undo, etc.
    </p>
  </body>
</html>
